<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
   <teiHeader>
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title>By the maior. The order of the House of Commons to the Lord Maior, for the due observing the Sabbath day.</title>
            <author>City of London (England). Lord Mayor.</author>
         </titleStmt>
         <editionStmt>
            <edition>
               <date>1641</date>
            </edition>
         </editionStmt>
         <extent>Approx. 4 KB of XML-encoded text transcribed from 1 1-bit group-IV TIFF page image.</extent>
         <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>Text Creation Partnership,</publisher>
            <pubPlace>Ann Arbor, MI ; Oxford (UK) :</pubPlace>
            <date when="2014-11">2014-11 (EEBO-TCP Phase 2).</date>
            <idno type="DLPS">B32508</idno>
            <idno type="STC">Interim Tract Supplement Guide 816.m.9[22]</idno>
            <idno type="STC">ESTC R215622</idno>
            <idno type="EEBO-CITATION">99884511</idno>
            <idno type="PROQUEST">ocm99884511</idno>
            <idno type="VID">185229</idno>
            <availability>
               <p>To the extent possible under law, the Text Creation Partnership has waived all copyright and related or neighboring rights to this keyboarded and encoded edition of the work described above, according to the terms of the CC0 1.0 Public Domain Dedication (http://creativecommons.org/publicdomain/zero/1.0/). This waiver does not extend to any page images or other supplementary files associated with this work, which may be protected by copyright or other license restrictions. Please go to https://www.textcreationpartnership.org/ for more information about the project.</p>
            </availability>
         </publicationStmt>
         <seriesStmt>
            <title>Early English books online text creation partnership.</title>
         </seriesStmt>
         <notesStmt>
            <note>(EEBO-TCP ; phase 2, no. B32508)</note>
            <note>Transcribed from: (Early English Books Online ; image set 185229)</note>
            <note>Images scanned from microfilm: (Early English books; Tract supplement ; C1:1[22])</note>
         </notesStmt>
         <sourceDesc>
            <biblFull>
               <titleStmt>
                  <title>By the maior. The order of the House of Commons to the Lord Maior, for the due observing the Sabbath day.</title>
                  <author>City of London (England). Lord Mayor.</author>
                  <author>Gurney, Richard, Sir, 1577-1647.</author>
                  <author>England and Wales. Parliament.</author>
               </titleStmt>
               <extent>1 sheet ([1] p.).   </extent>
               <publicationStmt>
                  <publisher>s.n.,</publisher>
                  <pubPlace>[London :</pubPlace>
                  <date>1641]</date>
               </publicationStmt>
               <notesStmt>
                  <note>The proclamation of the House of Commons is dated and signed: "This thirteenth of April, 1641. Mitchel.".</note>
                  <note>Reproduction of original in the British Library.</note>
               </notesStmt>
            </biblFull>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
      <encodingDesc>
         <projectDesc>
            <p>Created by converting TCP files to TEI P5 using tcp2tei.xsl,
      TEI @ Oxford.
      </p>
         </projectDesc>
         <editorialDecl>
            <p>EEBO-TCP is a partnership between the Universities of Michigan and Oxford and the publisher ProQuest to create accurately transcribed and encoded texts based on the image sets published by ProQuest via their Early English Books Online (EEBO) database (http://eebo.chadwyck.com). The general aim of EEBO-TCP is to encode one copy (usually the first edition) of every monographic English-language title published between 1473 and 1700 available in EEBO.</p>
            <p>EEBO-TCP aimed to produce large quantities of textual data within the usual project restraints of time and funding, and therefore chose to create diplomatic transcriptions (as opposed to critical editions) with light-touch, mainly structural encoding based on the Text Encoding Initiative (http://www.tei-c.org).</p>
            <p>The EEBO-TCP project was divided into two phases. The 25,368 texts created during Phase 1 of the project (2000-2009), initially available only to institutions that contributed to their creation, were released into the public domain on 1 January 2015. The approximately 40,000 texts produced during Phase 2 (2009- ), of which 34,963 had been released as of 2020, originally similarly restricted, were similarly freed from all restrictions on 1 August 2020. As of that date anyone is free to take and use these texts for any purpose (modify them, annotate them, distribute them, etc.). But we do respectfully request that due credit and attribution be given to their original source.</p>
            <p>Users should be aware of the process of creating the TCP texts, and therefore of any assumptions that can be made about the data.</p>
            <p>Text selection was based on the New Cambridge Bibliography of English Literature (NCBEL). If an author (or for an anonymous work, the title) appears in NCBEL, then their works are eligible for inclusion. Selection was intended to range over a wide variety of subject areas, to reflect the true nature of the print record of the period. In general, first editions of a works in English were prioritized, although there are a number of works in other languages, notably Latin and Welsh, included and sometimes a second or later edition of a work was chosen if there was a compelling reason to do so.</p>
            <p>Image sets were sent to external keying companies for transcription and basic encoding. Quality assurance was then carried out by editorial teams in Oxford and Michigan. 5% (or 5 pages, whichever is the greater) of each text was proofread for accuracy and those which did not meet QA standards were returned to the keyers to be redone. After proofreading, the encoding was enhanced and/or corrected and characters marked as illegible were corrected where possible up to a limit of 100 instances per text. Any remaining illegibles were encoded as &lt;gap&gt;s. Understanding these processes should make clear that, while the overall quality of TCP data is very good, some errors will remain and some readable characters will be marked as illegible. Users should bear in mind that in all likelihood such instances will never have been looked at by a TCP editor.</p>
            <p>The texts were encoded and linked to page images in accordance with level 4 of the TEI in Libraries guidelines.</p>
            <p>Copies of the texts have been issued variously as SGML (TCP schema; ASCII text with mnemonic sdata character entities); displayable XML (TCP schema; characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or text strings within braces); or lossless XML (TEI P5, characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or TEI g elements).</p>
            <p>Keying and markup guidelines are available at the <ref target="http://www.textcreationpartnership.org/docs/.">Text Creation Partnership web site</ref>.</p>
         </editorialDecl>
         <listPrefixDef>
            <prefixDef ident="tcp"
                       matchPattern="([0-9\-]+):([0-9IVX]+)"
                       replacementPattern="http://eebo.chadwyck.com/downloadtiff?vid=$1&amp;page=$2"/>
            <prefixDef ident="char"
                       matchPattern="(.+)"
                       replacementPattern="https://raw.githubusercontent.com/textcreationpartnership/Texts/master/tcpchars.xml#$1"/>
         </listPrefixDef>
      </encodingDesc>
      <profileDesc>
         <langUsage>
            <language ident="eng">eng</language>
         </langUsage>
         <textClass>
            <keywords scheme="http://authorities.loc.gov/">
               <term>Sabbath --  Early works to 1800.</term>
               <term>Broadsides --  England --  London --  17th century.</term>
            </keywords>
         </textClass>
      </profileDesc>
      <revisionDesc>
         <change>
            <date>2013-12</date>
            <label>TCP</label>Assigned for keying and markup</change>
         <change>
            <date>2013-12</date>
            <label>SPi Global</label>Keyed and coded from ProQuest page images</change>
         <change>
            <date>2014-02</date>
            <label>Anne Simpson</label>Sampled and proofread</change>
         <change>
            <date>2014-02</date>
            <label>Anne Simpson</label>Text and markup reviewed and edited</change>
         <change>
            <date>2014-03</date>
            <label>pfs</label>Batch review (QC) and XML conversion</change>
      </revisionDesc>
   </teiHeader>
   <text xml:lang="eng">
      <body>
         <div type="order">
            <pb facs="tcp:185229:1"/>
            <pb facs="tcp:185229:1" rendition="simple:additions"/>
            <head>By the Maior.</head>
            <head type="sub">The Order of the Houſe of Commons to the Lord <hi>Maior,</hi> for the due obſerving the Sabbath day.</head>
            <p>
               <hi>IT is this day ordered by the Houſe of Commons, that the Aldermen and Ci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tizens that ſerve for the Citie of</hi> London, <hi>ſhall intimate to the Lord</hi> Major, <hi>from this Houſe, that the Statutes, for the due obſerving of the Sab<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bath be put in execution. And it is further ordered that the like intimation from this Houſe be made to the Iuſtices of Peace in all the Counties of</hi> England <hi>and</hi> Wales. <hi>And the Knights of the Shire of the ſeverall Counties are to take care that Copies of this Order be accordingly ſent to the Iuſtices of Peace in the ſeve<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rall Counties.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>FOraſmuch as the Lords Day commonly called Sunday is of late much bro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ken and profaned by a diſorderly ſort of people in frequenting Taverns, Ale<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>houſes, and the like, and putting to ſale victuall and other things, and exerciſing unlawfull games and paſtimes, to the great diſhonour of God, and reproach of Religion, whereof the Houſe of Commons now aſſembled hath beene pleaſed to take notice, and by their order, intimation hath been given unto mee, that the Statutes for the due obſerving of the Sabbath be put in execution. Theſe are therefore in his Majeſties name to will and require you forthwith, upon the ſight hereof, that you give ſtrict charge and command unto all and every the Church-wardens and Conſtables within your Ward, that from henceforth they doe not permit or ſuffer any perſon or perſons, in the time of divine ſervice or at any other time upon the Sunday, to be drinking or playing in anie Tavern, Inne, Tobacco ſhop, Alehouſe or other victualling houſe whatſoever, nor ſuf<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fer any Fruiterer, Milkewomen, or Hearbwomen to ſtand with fruit, milk, herbs, or any other victuall or wares, in any the ſtreets, lanes, or allies within your ward, or any other wayes to put thoſe things or any other to ſale upon the Sun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>day at any time of the day or in the evening, nor to permit or ſuffer any per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſon or perſons to uſe or exerciſe upon that day any unlawfull exerciſes and paſt<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>times within your ward, and that expreſſe charge be given to every keeper of any Tavern, Inne, Cookſhouſe, Tobaccohouſe, Alehouſe, or any other Tipler or victualler whatſoever within your ward, that hereafter they receive not or ſuffer to remaine any perſon or perſons whatſoever as their gueſts or cuſtomers to tip<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ple eat drinke or take Tobacco in their houſes upon any Sunday, other then that Inholders may receive their ordinary gueſts, or travelers and ſuch like, who come to remain for a time in their Inne for diſpatch of their neceſſary buſineſſe. And if any perſon or perſons ſhall be found offending in the premiſſes that then they be brought before me the Lord <hi>Major,</hi> or ſome other of his Majeſties Juſtices of Peace, to the end they may receive ſuch puniſhment as to Juſtice ſhall appertain. And hereof not to fail as you will anſwer the contrary at your perill. This thir<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>teenth of <hi>April,</hi> 1641.</p>
            <closer>
               <signed>Mitchel.</signed>
            </closer>
         </div>
      </body>
   </text>
</TEI>
